[SPEAKER_01]: If I want to practice for the giving up of sensuality, how do I discern the difference between those sense objects that I have to give up and the ones that are fine?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, you don't... it's not even the sense objects that you have to give up.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's your engagement with them.
[SPEAKER_00]: It needs to be controlled or restrained.
[SPEAKER_00]: And what determines that is the passion behind that engagement.
[SPEAKER_00]: So... because sense objects will present themselves whether you like it or not.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even the, let's say, the bad ones that have the potential to induce passion,
[SPEAKER_00]: Even if you live completely isolated from the whole world, as the Buddha said, the sixth sense space is the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: That one's always with you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means, at any point, the bad sense objects can still show up.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you can't give it up in that sense, except by trying to control the circumstances, which will always fail sooner or later, and that's never going to lead to any stable kind of freedom.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you understand it's about the engagement, then you realize, well, what's the course's type of engagement I can have?
[SPEAKER_00]: It's physical engagement.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that's why it starts with the precepts.
[SPEAKER_00]: You will still encounter pretty much the same sense objects throughout your life.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's inevitable, to some extent.
[SPEAKER_00]: But how far you engage with them, you start to put a limit on that.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's what the precepts do.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you have done that,
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, you can start to see how you engage with sense objects, even on the mental level, which is then the practice of sense restraint.
[SPEAKER_00]: As it is described, grasping signs and features of sights in such a way that... or sounds, smells, tastes and touches in such a way that lust or aversion arise,
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what you abstain from.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like grasping signs and features in such a way.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's all now on the level of your mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: How you kind of give your or direct your attention at these objects that come up.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, see, it's a... even though for people who haven't kept the precepts sufficiently, it doesn't seem that way.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is a difference between something
[SPEAKER_00]: Just kind of appearing, even mentally.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, you choosing to kind of engage it, engage with it, and sort of extract the pleasure from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you always have that difference, which is why you feel the kind of... that kind of like dissonance or dissatisfaction when you start keeping the precepts and you haven't been doing it before.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have this... in a way, you have the same object.
[SPEAKER_00]: That kind of present to your senses, but you're not extracting enough from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're not kind of going far enough, whatever arbitrary threshold you're used to in your engagement with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's that engagement of like... For example,
[SPEAKER_00]: Celibacy, like for an average person who's not used to it, simply coming across attractive people and not engaging in or trying to initiate any kind of sexual interactions and just not making efforts in that direction, that's already going to kind of leave them feeling that sort of void of not getting the amount of engagement that they're used to.
[SPEAKER_00]: Technically, I'm still seeing all the things that I would have engaged with before, but just I'm not engaging with it enough.
[SPEAKER_00]: When you expand that same principle to the mental level, you realize the same applies.
[SPEAKER_00]: Things appear vaguely, sort of like a blurry perception of some sensual thing, and then your mind wants to sort of latch onto it and dwell on it more.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you don't allow that.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you don't, in the same way as like a person would be present in the room, but you know that you're celibate, you're not going to make any efforts to connect with them on a sexual level, you, in the same way, you're not going to make any effort to further expand
[SPEAKER_00]: This sensual perception that arose just in a mental level.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, even if it stays there for days, nothing unwholesome will have happened, unless you made that choice of expanding on it, focusing on it, kind of, like I said, trying to extract more from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you will feel that same sort of, like, eh... like void, like you're not, kind of, getting what you expect from it, even though it's there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sort of floating around ambiguously.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's exactly then how you start to realize it's not really the... it's not the sense objects.
[SPEAKER_00]: It never was the sense objects.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's that engagement that you... that you... that it really is what your mind craves for.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's basically like this kind of secondary distraction
[SPEAKER_00]: That blurs that painful void that you feel when you see something attractive.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why, for example, when you have... are giving in to something, like something you desire,
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, all of a sudden, it's not that it's taken away completely, but you're just kind of temporarily interrupted in your engagement.
[SPEAKER_00]: You already feel the pain, even though you didn't lose it, which is what most people would think.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, oh, you feel pain because I lost it externally.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, if I still had it, if the person hadn't died or whatever, like, I wouldn't be suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then, you realize
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, but that's really secondary.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's never about the person or about the object.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's... that engagement allows you a kind of like a temporary escape from the pain that the desirable thing exerts simply due to its presence.
[SPEAKER_00]: And why is that the case?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, that's just how existence is.
[SPEAKER_00]: As the Buddha said, the sense organs themselves are painful.
[SPEAKER_00]: Six sense bases.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's like that, actually, like that simile of the of the leper.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, burning his wounds in the charcoal pit provides him this kind of temporary relief from the itching of his wounds, while at the same time making it worse.
[SPEAKER_00]: Increasing his dependence on needing to... Like, see, both in the terms that the leprosy gets worse, and also in the sense that he's going to be even less able to to put up with the itch when it arises on its own, without going to the charcoal pit.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's the dependence on sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which, yes, it has something to do with the object.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not completely separate from it, because nobody would seek that gratification from something that's not pleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: It has to be pleasant first.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why the Buddha defined the five strings of sensuality as things that are agreeable.
[SPEAKER_00]: Enticing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Otherwise, it could not be a means for that temporary distraction.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not going to captivate you enough for you to start ignoring the painful desire that's underneath.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's almost like kind of...
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not that the pain goes away, which is why you need to keep escalating your engagement.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's really just... it allows you to sort of not have to think about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not have to think about that underlying pain of craving that's actually driving your engagement, because the engagement comes with all this pleasure and all these details for you to focus on.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in other words, the whole realm of sensuality is just maybe the coarsest form of distraction?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, well, it's a cover, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's a means for you to, well, ignore the pain that comes with the sensual desire itself, while increasing the desire through ignoring it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, again, it's not that...
[SPEAKER_00]: Sometimes people think, if I give in enough, and I get enough experience with sensuality, then, naturally, I won't be as interested in it as before.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's completely based on their misconception that sensuality is in the objects.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, yes, if you eat the same food for 10 years, you're going to be bored.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that has absolutely nothing to do with that mechanism of when you see something that is attractive.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that food is not going to be attractive when you've been eating it after 10 years, but that doesn't count then.
[SPEAKER_00]: When you find something that is actually attractive to you,
[SPEAKER_00]: Are you then pressured immediately to engage with it further?
[SPEAKER_00]: To latch on to its details?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if you are, then that's what sensuality is.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what the sensual desire is.
[SPEAKER_00]: So then, if you are honest with yourself, you'll see that never stops.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can
[SPEAKER_00]: Scratch the itch to the point where very few things that you can encounter on a regular enough basis are attractive.
[SPEAKER_00]: But something will still be attractive to you.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it just gets more and more extreme, more and more refined.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which really means you're just confining yourself further and further.
[SPEAKER_00]: Narrowing down your avenue of escape.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why even for people who were not going to practice and try to free their minds from craving, it was still better for them to contain their sensual desires as much as possible, because then you actually have more things to... to even... even wrongly, but like to... to kind of appease that itch.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whereas the more you give into it,
[SPEAKER_00]: The narrower and narrower both things become, like your ability to get the sensual verification and your ability to escape from sensuality altogether.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why there's no benefit whatsoever if your aim is to practice, to give in.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, yeah, while you might become more familiar with certain things and stop craving them, that habit of something
[SPEAKER_00]: Pressuring you towards it, towards engagement, is going to be completely unchanged.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it doesn't end with sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like that, that whole energy, let's say, that you're building up through those actions, that translates to all the hindrances.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, like, somebody who has been seeking this engagement with sensual objects is, to that same extent, going to be even less able to put up with the discomfort of things not going their way, more prone to aversion, laziness, restlessness, doubts, because it's the same principle.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, something unpleasant comes up,
[SPEAKER_00]: And you just have to act out of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have to, because that's the principle of craving in general, like how it provides some sort of relief to give into it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like two completely separate things.
[SPEAKER_00]: The discomfort that you feel, and then this sort of activity that you engage in, that makes you not have to look at it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's like... that's why, in fact, the Buddha said one of the fundamental defilements, āsavas, is ignorance.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not in some mystical, cosmic lack of knowledge.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's that same sort of... you could almost say, like a belief or a view, that engagement functions as a solution from pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which doesn't mean like you won't do anything, if you understand that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the problem isn't action either.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's action done specifically with that purpose of covering up that discomfort underneath, which is what actually makes it hurt.
[SPEAKER_00]: The fact that you're trying to to mask it, whichever means necessary, rather than understanding this is what existence is.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, you will have absolutely no need to seek pleasant objects, which is really what sensuality is, not whether they are there in the world.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the theme of not distracting yourself could actually be a theme that you can take from the courses to the subtlest
[SPEAKER_01]: phenomena of existence, like in the beginning, you have the coarse versions, but then actually distracting yourself from basic facts of existence.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, but you have to, you have to always keep it organic, like not kind of abstractly thinking about, oh, distracting myself.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm distracting myself because I'm deciding to, I don't know, read a book.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means I'm trying to escape from the raw discomfort of existence.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, are you?
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, that's not just something you decide, or it's not something that's inherent to the action.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have to see, is there something unpleasant that I'm trying to run away from?
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, I actually have the view that this will disappear.
[SPEAKER_00]: This will be fixed.
[SPEAKER_00]: This discomfort will be fixed if I read this book.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's when you're actually acting out of hindrance.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it would be completely fine to read the book if it doesn't distract me?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, if it doesn't have that implication of a relief from this kind of pressure, then yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then whatever reason you would be reading the book for wouldn't be unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, obviously, you know, it's not going to be perfect in the beginning, and you might have doubts and be reading books about the dhamma and stuff to kind of deal with all of it, but it's certainly something you should start to discern as being rooted in your intentions, as we always say, so that eventually you realize it's not even just... in the same way as with sensuality, like
[SPEAKER_01]: It always depends on your intentions.
[SPEAKER_00]: There are certain things that are always wrong, but fundamentally it depends on your intentions.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, in the same way, it's not that you're automatically justified in, for example, reading about the dhamma because it's the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: If it's coming out of that similar compulsion, that like this engagement will mask the pain,
[SPEAKER_00]: That just pain of your mind being wound up with something, maybe not even related, necessarily.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, you have to see, wait, this is unwholesome as well, then, regardless of the content.